Why start with C in in 20 26?
>> It is
a wonderful foundation on which to build
your understanding of how a computer
works and how software is built. It's
about as close as you can get to the
hardware before things devolve, at least
aesthetically, into assembly code, which
is much scarier-looking code, I think,
for most people, almost everyone,
perhaps.
Um and certainly, uh beyond that is
zeros and ones, which is not going to be
fun for anyone. Um so, C kind of
strikes, I think, pedagogically this
really nice balance of having
English-like syntax and abstractions on
top of lower-level primitives that allow
you to explore procedural programming,
uh in particular, with some fundamental
what constructs that are now fundamental
to those kinds of languages, loops and
conditions and functions and variables
and return values and so forth. It's
sort of got It's got everything, but
it's also a pretty small language, and
unless you download third-party stuff,
there's not a very large standard
library, in fact. So, most anything you
want, you need to build yourself. And
so, we leverage this significantly in
CS50, so much so that by mid-semester,
in week five of the class, students are
building their own hash tables, and
we're talking about how you could
construct singly linked, doubly linked
lists, uh hash tables and tries, uh
trees, abstract data types like stacks
and queues and so many more. And what I
think is especially meaningful about C
is that you can't just instantiate one
of those data structures if you want
one, like you can in Java and C++ with
STL and certain other libraries. Like,
if you want it, you're going to have to
build it yourself. And I think that
alone is a good educational exercise,
not because you're going to need to
build that thing again, but because
there's value, I think, in really
understanding from the bottom up what is
going on inside of that device, so that,
one, you can make more informed
decisions as to how you want to engineer
and design your own data structures down
the line. Two, you can
diagnose problems by reasoning through
first principles what could possibly go
wrong because you understand how the
data is being stored and what the
algorithms are that are performing on
that data. Um and three, it's a
wonderful scaffold to higher level
languages because one of my favorite
things from week five to six in CS50 is
students go from having written the week
in week five like their own hash tables
implementation
uh for adding data, retrieving data, and
so forth, which is like this many lines
of code for some font size. And it it
gets whittled down in week six to one
line where you just instantiate a Python
dictionary. But and you can be
productive with a dictionary and many
courses do teach programming by way of
Python alone and we too have done it for
some of our audiences.
But you really never get around to
understanding what's going on underneath
the hood. And our goal in CS50 among
them is not to
uh output programmers, but engineers and
educated citizens and folks who really
understand from first principles how
technology works. And so C for instance
strikes, I think just that right
balance. And for those students who want
to go even deeper in a systems class,
they can go learn about assembly and
compilers and so forth. Um but those
students who want to go on to web
programming or data science stuff or AI
nowadays can just build on top of the C
and then in turn Python um layers that
we use in the class.
>> I was doing research and I saw a YouTube
video that said, "Whatever you do, don't
take CS50." Clickbait, whatever.
>> Okay. Yeah, I So I watched the video.
>> Uh-huh.
>> And the person's So it worked.
>> Yeah, it got me. It got me. And the
perspective of the author of this video
was that CS50 teaches you all this stuff
that you don't really need to know if
you were like a full stack engineer or
something. Like if you if I was just
going into the industry and I'm just
making web apps or, you know, whatever
and using JavaScript or
that a lot of this um underlying stuff
you you might not need and so maybe it's
not a good use of time. And I'm curious
what you would say to someone that has
that that mindset that you don't need to
actually know how the computer works.
>> I don't want to get into a whole
internet fight here, but I think that is
absolutely the wrong mindset, certainly
for a full stack engineer. I mean, by
definition of full stack, you should be
understanding everything that's
happening among those layers. So, I
think the better formulation isn't that
you don't need to know these things, but
rather you won't need to use these
things. Use in a literal sense. Like, I
don't my C is a very popular language,
even according to some rankings each
year is, you know, the number one,
number two language in terms of its
omnipresence still to this day, because
it's very highly performant. Um
Albeit more challenging to write than
some languages. I only use C for 5 weeks
during CS50 itself, but that doesn't
mean that it hasn't helped me understand
higher-level languages, what is going on
inside of a system, how you can improve
the performance of the design of some
system by understanding, again, those
first principles.
Uh I don't use Scratch except for 1 week
out of the year. I do use Python more
frequently, and I use JavaScript and
some HTML and CSS, but I think if you're
going to call yourself an engineer, you
should absolutely
have mastery of and knowledge of those
underlying building blocks if you want
to not just output something that
frankly AI could output nowadays, but
you can understand and you can create
the next thing or the solution to some
other problem that we haven't even yet
solved. Um I think that's the better
mindset, to appreciate, yes, I'm not
going to need to use Scratch or C or
maybe some of the other things we touch
on in CS50, but the knowledge and the
principles that we extract from those
implementation details are incredibly
valuable. If you want to be an engineer
and not just say uh a coder, is which is
a distinction that some folks might
make.